Guide to the Katherine Shapleigh Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Katherine Shapleigh Papers
1887-1976
RG 176
Yale University Divinity School Library
2
(5 boxes)
Letters, writings, photographs, and collected material document the fascinating life of Katherine Shapleigh, including her missionary work in China. Raised as a traditional Episcopalian, Katherine Chase Pratt Shapleigh married Alfred Shapleigh, a graduate of Harvard Medical School, and they served in Tientsin, China under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions from 1896 to 1897. Apparently experiencing a transformation in their religious beliefs, the Shapleighs divested themselves of many of the wedding gifts and possessions given to them by their affluent families and returned to the U.S. where Alfred attended Bible schools and they engaged in home mission work until able to return to China under the more conservative China Inland Mission board. They returned to China in 1904 but Alfred and their two children tragically died of smallpox shortly after arrival. Katherine Shapleigh remained in China under the CIM for several years (1904-1908, 1915-1920, 1926-1927). She served at the training school for future mission workers run by the China Inland Mission in Yangchow and in later years worked with Russian refugees at the Foreign Women's Home in Shanghai. Shapleigh later served as Dean of Women at Wheaton College in Illinois.
Shapleigh, Katherine, 1875-1942
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Stephen D. Pratt and Joan Morgan Anderson.
Biographical / Historical
1875Dec 29 Born in Worcester, MA
1892-1893 Attended St. Agnes School, Albany, NY
1895 Met Alfred Shapleigh in Princeton, MA where their families had summer homes
1896Jun 2 Married Alfred Shapleigh; they had three children: Samuel Brooks (1897-1905), Gordon (1899-1900), Stephen (1903-1905).
1896-1897 Served in Tientsin, China under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions
1897 Family returned to Worcester, MA, where Alfred took over practice of physician who was on leave
1898-1899 Moved to Boston, where Alfred was assistant to his father, who was president of the Shapleigh Coffee Co., and engaged in Bible study
1900 Alfred took Bible training courses at Nyack College in New York and Moody Bible Institute in Chicago
1901 Engaged in evangelistic home missionary work in California
1901-1902 Returned to Boston; worked with Salvation Army
1902-1903 Home missionary work in Colorado and California
1904 Returned to China under China Inland Mission
1905 Alfred and two surviving sons died of smallpox shortly after the family's arrival in China. Alfred and the sons had not been vaccinated against smallpox, so did not survive the disease; Katherine suffered a mild case of smallpox but recovered.
1905-1908 Katherine remained in China, engaging in language study and serving at missionary training school in Yangchow
1908 KS returned to U.S. where she cared for her father and spoke in churches
1915-1916 In Yangchow, followed by return to U.S.
1918-1920 Working with women Russian refugees at Foreign Women's Home, Shanghai, followed by return to U.S.
1926-1927 Working at Foreign Women's Home, Shanghai
ca. 1934 Appointed Dean of Women at Wheaton College, Wheaton, IL
1935 Received B.A.
1937 Following a severe heart attack, KS retired from Wheaton position and moved to North Carolina
1942 Died in NC
Scope and Contents
Series I, Correspondence consists primarily of family correspondence. Letters from Shapleigh to her family and their replies document in detail the changing paths of her life. Brought up in an affluent, traditional Episcopalian household, Katherine may have been headed toward a rather sheltered existence, but her marriage to Alfred Shapleigh and their subsequent work in China exposed her to a vastly different world. The Shapleighs' dissatisfaction during their first period of work in China under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions led to a return back to the United States where they engaged in a variety of educational, commercial, and missionary activities before being appointed by the China Inland Mission to return to China. The tragic deaths of Katherine's husband and sons shortly after their arrival in China did not deter her from remaining with the mission and finding a new way of life there. While Katherine had been largely preoccupied by her language study and baby son during their first period in China, her subsequent years alone in China were spent at the CIM Yangchow training school and the Foreign Women's Home in Shanghai, which provided shelter to Russian women refugees who came to China following the Bolshevik revolution in Russia. Katherine found fulfillment in her work with her mission colleagues but clearly had continuing strong ties to her family at home. In addition to the correspondence documenting Shapleigh's life, there are also letters of other family members and material related to the John Singer Sargent portrait of Katherine that was painted when she was in her late teen years.
Series II, Writings, includes some early school essays but consists primarily of poetry written by Katherine Shapleigh. Katherine was an accomplished poet who had her work published.
Series III, Personal Items and Memorabilia, includes a variety of materials documenting Katherine Shapleigh's life, from early school report cards to biographical sketches by family members. Of particular note in this section is the application letter submitted by Katherine to the China Inland Mission when she and her husband sought appointment to China by CIM. This autobiographical letter provides explanation of the religious beliefs that significantly influenced the course of the Shapleighs' lives. Series III also includes a number of interesting photographs from the Shapleighs' early years in China, 1896-1897, which show their well-equipped Western-style home in China, their Chinese language teachers, and so forth. Later photographs show Katherine in Yangchow and members of the China Inland Mission Kiangsu Conference.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia
Missions -- China; Missionaries; Shapleigh, Katherine, 1875-1942; China Inland Mission
- Correspondence, Series I
  - KS to family
    - Childhood letters to parents, 1887-1892 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - To parents while at St. Agnes School, Albany, NY, 1893 Jun- Oct 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - From St. Agnes School, 1893 Oct 12-1894 Nov (Box 1, Folder 4-9)
    - To parents, incl. honeymoon, 1896 Mar-Jul (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - To family, en route to China, 1896 Aug-Sep (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - To family, from Tientsin, 1896 Sep-Oct (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - From Tientsin, 1896 Nov-1897 Feb (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
    - From Tientsin, incl. birth of son, Samuel Brooks, 1897 Mar-Apr (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - From Tientsin and Pei-Tai-Ho (vacation resort), 1897 May (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - From Pei-Tai-Ho, 1897 Jun-Aug (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
    - From Tientsin, 1897 Sep-Nov (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - From USA / Princeton, Allston, MA, 1898 Jun - 1899 Dec (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
    - From USA, 1900 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
    - From USA / California, 1901 Jan-Apr (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - From USA / California, Allston, MA, 1901 May-Dec (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - From USA, 1902 Jan-1903 Oct (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
    - From USA / En route to China, 1904 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - From Shanghai, Chinkiang, incl. death of Alfred and sons, 1905 Jan-Apr (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - From Yangchow, 1905 May-Dec (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
    - From Yangchow, Chinkiang, 1906 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - From Chinkiang, Shanghai, 1907 Jan-Feb (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - From USA, 1908 Apr-1914 (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
    - From USA / En route to China / Yangchow, 1915 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - From Yangchow, etc., 1916 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - From China, various / From USA, Baltimore, 1917 Jan-Nov (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - En route to China / From Tsinan, 1918 Aug-Dec (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - From Tsinan, Kuling, Shanghai, 1919 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - From Foreign Women's Home, Shanghai (work with Russian refugees), 1920 Jan-Oct. (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - From Foreign Women's Home, Shanghai, 1926-1927 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Traveling in Europe, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - From Wheaton College, 1934-1937 (Box 3, Folder 45-46)
  - Circular Letters of KS
    - From China Inland Mission station in Yangchow / Yang-chow; incl. re. death and funeral of J. Hudson Taylor, 1905-1906 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - From family to KS
    - Parents, 1893 Sep-1906 Nov (Box 3, Folder 48-55)
    - Sister, 1905-1906, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 56-58)
    - Brothers, 1904, 1906, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Mother-in-law, 1905 Feb-Mar (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Father-in-law, 1905 Feb-Apr (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Sister-in-law, 1905 Feb-Apr (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - KS to / from others
    - Miscellaneous letters to KS (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Letters re. KS heart attack, Wheaton, 1937 Jun-Sep (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Correspondence of others
    - Frederick Pratt (father) to/from various people (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Arthur Shapleigh, Sr. to Frederick Pratt, 1895, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Elizabeth (sister) to parents, 1888-1893 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Letters re. loan of John Singer Sargent portrait of Katherine Shapleigh, 1893-1946 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Re. insurance policies on paintings, 1924, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Letters from John S. Sargent and photos, 1890 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Fragments and unidentified; Partial log of "Aunt Kitty" letters compiled by Stephen D. Pratt (Box 4, Folder 71)
- Writings of KS, Series II
  - Early school essays, 1890s (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Poetry, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 73-75)
  - Correspondence re. publishing poetry (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Article: "A Visit to a New Station", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 77)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series III
  - Letters of condolence upon death of husband and sons, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Birth, wedding certificates; will of ALS, consular papers (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Letters from Brooks (son) to grandparents, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Booklets and programs (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Childhood report cards; French and Latin letters to/from KS and brother (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Early school notes and workbooks of KS (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Catalogs re. works of John Singer Sargent (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Miscellaneous, incl. cable codes, letter re. gravestone (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Biographical information: incl. autobiographical letters by KS and AS to China Inland Mission board, family tree, biographical sketch of KS by sister Elizabeth Pratt Clark, Katharine Irving Morgan's Tuesday Club Paper on "Aunt Kitty", delivered in March 1976, 1896-1976 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Photographs: KS, family, home in China, Chinese language teachers, 1897-1897 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Photographs: KS, family, missionaries on ship to China, 1904 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Photographs: KS, colleagues in Yangchow, China Inland Mission Kiang-su Conference, 1906-1907 (Box 5, Folder 87)